A Guide to the Memorabilia of Robert T. Canevari
Special Collections, University of Virginia Library
Special Collections, University of Virginia Library
Memorabilia of Robert T. Canevari 1973-1999
Special Collections, University of Virginia Library
12818
167 items, one and half Hollinger boxes, one cubic and 2 linear feet
Robert T. Canevari
Administrative Information
Access Restrictions
Access restrictions apply under the terms of the Family Educational Rights and Privacy Act (F.E.R.P.A.) to student papers (Folder: 9)
Acquisition Information
The collection was given to Special Collections by Robert T. Canevari on July 9, 1999.
Biographical/Historical Information
Robert T. Canevari served as the Dean of Students at the University of Virginia from 1970 to 1999. He also served as acting interim Vice President of Student Affairs (1993-1994.) Dean Canevari began his work at the University as a student in 1955. He played football for the Cavaliers for two of his four years. He also served in the Army ROTC after graduating from the Education School in 1960. He became Assistant Dean of Students in 1965 under Dean B. F. D. Runk. Described as enthusiastic and caring, Dean Canevari had a gift of making students feel comfortable. Associate Dean of Students V. Shamim Sisson said of Canevari, "his most important contribution he has given over the years has been himself." He helped students during the Vietnam War protests and also through the continuing cultural changes in student life during an era of dramatic growth and diversification at the University. In 1984 the University showed their appreciation by giving him one of their highest honors, the Algernon Sydney Sullivan award which was given annually to a member of the University Community for their "high qualities of heart and mind" in serving the University. The citation read "As a loyal and trustworthy individual Mr. Canevari may always be relied upon for an honest opinion exhibiting a remarkable degree of empathy." He was also given an award by the Seven Society and had a scholarship established by former students and friends in his name to honor his contributions to the University. Canevari loved working with the students so much that he couldn't believe he was paid to do it.
Scope and Content
The collection consists of correspondence of University of Virginia Dean of Students Robert T. Canevari, newspaper clippings about Canevari and his appearance on "A Closer Look" with Jane Pauley, and Office of the Dean of Students reports. Of interest is a letter from Amy Garrou, Assistant Dean of Admissions to the Society of Purple Shadows criticizing the use of their robes and hoods. There is a response from the Society defending their position to Dean Canevari. There are also notes from students, a card from the Society, and a paperback book titled, "The Shadow Laughs"
There are also trophies and gifts from students and the University including an American Flag that was flown at the Capitol for Canevari in appreciation for his allowing the use of Newcomb Hall for the Virginia Congressional Delegation Academy Day on March 20, 1993. Other awards include the Algernon Sydney Sullivan plague, a resolution commending Canevari for his twenty nine years of service to the students of the University of Virginia and several trophies for his dedication to the University of Virginia. The collection is 167 items, one and half Hollinger boxes and one cubic and 2 linear feet.
Arrangement
The collection is arranged alphabetically by topic and chronologically within each folder
Contents List
- Personal Correspondence 1984-19851990-1999n.d., 21 items (Box-folder 1:1)
  Included is a note from the Seven Society that probably came with an award. There is also a note from the Director of the Peace Corps that came attached to an award, and a letter from a student that gave him a present (maybe the bow and arrow and quiver) from Santiago.
- Media Event "A Closer Look" with Jane Pauley 1991, 10 items (Box-folder 1:2)
  There are newspaper articles and photographs about the national story that Pauley did on UVA students and typical student life, including an interview with Robert T. Canevari
- Newspaper clippings Canevari 1979-1995, 14 items (Box-folder 1:3)
- Newspaper clippings and articles (miscellaneous) 1979-1998, 75 items (Box-folder 1:4)
  There are articles that Canevari probably kept as ideas for motivating and inspiring students
- Office of Dean of Students Program Development Models 1980 Fall, 1 notebook (Box-folder 1:5)
- Office of Dean of Students Reports 1977-1984, four notebooks (Box-folder 1:6)
- Office of Dean of Students Self Study 1973, 1 notebook (Box-folder 1:7)
- Photographs n. d., 2 items (Box-folder 1:8)
  Photograph of the Rotunda and a photograph of a student Lisa Kersey
- Residence Life Programs 1981-1984, 4 items (Box-folder 1:9)
- Society of the Purple Shadows 1997, 4 items (Box-folder 1:10)
  There is a letter from Amy Garrou, Assistant Dean of Admissions to the Society of Purple Shadows criticizing the use of robes and hoods. There is also a letter from the Society defending their position to Dean Canevari. There are also notes from students, a card from the Society, and a paperback book titled, "The Shadow Laughs" These items were originally in a cigar box.
- Restricted (Box-folder 2:1)
  - Student Papers 1975-1989, 15 items (Box-folder 2:1)
- Cubic
  Cubic:
  1994 Algernon Sydney Sullivan Award
  1999 Trophy from The Peace Corp to Robert T. Canevari for his friendship
  1999 UVA Greek Award for Lifetime Faculty Contribution to the Greek System
  1993-1994 Silver Plate for Bob Canevari Interim Vice President for Student Affairs
  Incarnate Memories Prevail (IMP) Society Trophy to Robert Terence Canevari
  (UVA graduate 1992) Insignia of the 4484 th Test Squadron and photograph of pilot, Lt.Colonel Tom Devine's F-15A airplane
  Certificate for United States of America Flag flown over the Capital for Canevari and Flag included (need to put in a separate box)
  SR-99-18 Resolution honoring Canevari
  1994 Certificate of award establishing the Robert T. Canevari Award for commitment to fostering civility and diversity by the members of the Resident Staff Program
  Artifacts given to Robert T. Canevari by his students, friends, and colleagues: miniature quiver and bow and arrow, Lewis Glaser goose quill pen set, miniature replica of a dead sea scroll from Chris Stevens, candlestick with a bell attached to the base, miniature document inside an engraved paperweight replicating a Barringer Rennovation Associates document, embroidery by Lisa Kersey, and a decorated bottle of wine (empty)